and
we're gonna keep talking about
bodhichitta and what it feels like and
the next section he says
uh if you take
the first steps to bodhichitta which is
thinking about all people equally uh
equanimity
and then
uh
recognizing that people have been your
mom
remembering what they did for you when
they were your mom
and then wanting to pay them back for
what they did to you for you when they
were your mom
those steps are the foundation
for wanting to work for others okay so
they lay the foundation what are the
foundation think of everybody as equal
recognize they've been your mom
remember what they did for you
and
you know not actually then you want to
pay them back so those four which is
really three and a half
are the foundation
of wanting to work for other people okay
then he says the other ones which is
wanting those people to be happy
wanting to take away all their trouble
and [__] some
i'm the i'm taking care of it
i don't care if nobody helps me i don't
even care if
people try to stop me
okay do you care if people help you nah
i'm willing to do it on my own do you
care if people actively try to stop you
nope i don't even care about that
i'm the man or woman okay i'm the one
it's on me
what's that it's on me it's my bad it's
my good uh
i'll take care of everything okay i'll
take everything those things those ideas
i want you to be happy
i want to take away all your problems
and i'm the man or the woman i'll take
care of it i'll take care of it nobody
helps me i don't care
everyone fights to me i don't care i'll
still help you
okay so those three are called shendon
look
uh
the real desire
to to work for others okay so the first
part of those seven
was called
laying the groundwork
for working for others and now we're to
the working further okay these are
working for this okay here's the
work for others picture
i'm on it
okay he's got his construction hat looks
like daniel right on a good day
uh i'm i'm on it don't worry
i got my hat
i'm taking care of this
hey
nobody's gonna help you i don't care
everyone's going to fight you i also
don't care
okay it's on me i'll take care of it
okay
and then he and then he goes to a very
famous place they named
once you
once you kind of decided
that you're going to work for other
people
we could say
so
[Music]
the definition of bunny chinner the
definition the most famous definition in
history
of bodhichitta tim who wrote it
who wrote the abyss
which a certain new translator is going
to be working on
yeah my dream okay
so this is from the book that tim's
translating
uh
which is called the
the jewel of realizations
written 1700
years ago
and he mentions the definition of
bodhichitta and it's been famous ever
since then
they do okay
so in your you're in a debate in the
monasteries
what's the definition of bodhichitta you
just lay that out and you're covered
okay
who's definition the future buddha
is he a buddha yet or not ah now that's
a question
that was my pre geshe
debate topic uh anyway
uh
sengay bunny what is the definition of
bodhichitta here's the translation of
those two lines okay what is the
definition of buddhism
for the sake of other people
i want to become a buddha okay so it's
called the two focused attitude
two focuses you know
focused on
other people and
buddhahood okay it's called two focus
and two focuses the attitude with two
focuses
i'm looking at all the suffering beings
in the universe
and i want to become a buddha for them
that's the definition of buddhism okay
uh focused
on all the people having trouble in this
world
i want to be someone who can help them
and and that's the definition of
buddhism it's called two
two-part focus okay
all right
i i thought it'd be fun to memorize the
censoring
it was written in sanskrit sanskrit is
the language of the gods
you know uh
this line is very very very very famous
you know so
they say
if you want to plant a seed in your
heart
to become an enlightened being memorize
a little sense once in a while okay
so i i went got it for you okay
and uh i got the new dad to
convert the sanskrit for me
uh
when you see that macron long mark over
the a
you say it twice as long
okay so say chitto
[Music]
is a french nizzle they always talk like
the nose is stuck stuffed up
[Music]
here we go together slow okay whole
thing one
two
very slow
[Music]
okay good
try to memorize as sexy okay
if you get
lazy about the long vowels and stuff you
could use the second one
okay
yes
[Music]
means to give rise to
but when the chitta meets upadha
it changes to chittopadha
when a meets you it changes to o okay so
chitta
upadaya
sorry
it means to raise the mind it means to
raise the thought it means to reach
bodhichitta uh there's two words for
bodhichitta in sanskrit one is
bodhichitta
and one is chitopada this is the
varian
okay
uh para
para means
uh other people
what is what is it called when you go to
the other side
okay so here para means other people
other side okay
what's artha like siddhartha
the goal okay so paratha means the goals
of other people okay
paratha means the goals of other people
what other people want what other people
need is called paratha okay
ayah at the
end of a word means for the sake of that
in order to achieve that okay
so the ayah
on the end of paratha
means for the
for
for the goals of others for the goals of
others the aya aya means four
okay so
prepositions in sanskrit come after the
word and they're joined to the word
like for cat
for cotton okay
for
cotton
means for cotton
means enlightenment okay
some means perfect
body means enlightenment okay
to to to wish to achieve okay
means mind right
mental comes from that mind comes from
that
ah means very much at the beginning of a
word
a along a means very much that's why we
call the buddhist disciple
ahmanda which means super happy guy
instead of ananda which means the
unhappy guy
okay
so long a at the beginning means very
much
[Music]
really wanted really
obsessed with thinking about
perfect total enlightenment for the sake
of others okay
it's the definition of
chitopa
or bodhichitta okay
so you should learn it okay you guys
should learn it
okay and uh it all has pieces of chitta
parus
okay i consider you
or i read right so chitta
in russian sanskrit roots are much more
obvious
okay so anyway chitta means to think
uh but
to fall down for example
some guy wrote a book
yeah what's that guy's name
yeah it all means foot or fall or drop
okay
so
here oop oop
means
means to
to raise the desire for
buddhahood but to raise the thought
chitopada okay
like siddhartha okay say what's
siddhartha mean
what's the siddha
achieved
achieve the goal siddhartha
my mind is on it okay i'm mata okay cool
try to memorize it it's good all right
i like to call it next picture too
yeah
before that actually
[Music]
yeah there's an emphasis in the
definition of bodhichitta that you are
looking ahead to the future
you know i want that
i want to achieve that oops sorry you
guys
i want to achieve that to help all
living people okay there's a looking
ahead okay
uh i i i would like to achieve that so
that i could really help people okay
cool
all right
so pablo korempiche at this point in the
book
gives the most famous lines ever written
about bodhichitta okay and they're
written by
my tran
who was taking dictation
[Music]
what famous school did arya sanga help
start
mind
what famous school did his brother start
tap brother
what's in common between those two
startings
wait who said the first thing
no i want something else
[Music]
i'll say it again collect your money
from ellie okay we have a new system
it's not her problem to give you your
money you have to ask for it we're
trusting that the whole universe only
asks for money that they want
uh
yeah
yeah the cool thing about these two half
brothers
is that in their heart
they are both middle way they are both
higher middleway
but
because the students around them were
dull and less dull
or dull and mordo
they dumbed it down they made it more
simple
and masterbuster bandu created uh you
know reports the abhidharma
and in a way uh
arya sangha is just reporting the mind
only
and we've been having a lot of fun
lately with the mind only school's
presentation on seeds
which is the best
and where some compass says not too
shabby maybe we'll include it in the
middle you see he says so kappa praises
it highly
the middle the mind only presentation on
seeds
he says very useful for tantra
very useful for tantra so wow that's
like
must be cool right
all right
daniel's right
that's very difficult question i should
give you more money but nah
okay
uh
all right good
uh here we go
uh
now he's talking about look
let's talk about
what's complete bodhichitta what is if
you if someone said
what's the definition of complete
bodhichitta
here's pablanca
senior suzuba semkelani
if you want to talk about
bodhichitta
which is totally
complete
it's not enough
that
you kind of want to achieve
buddhahood
because other people need it he says
it's not enough he pabonka says that's
that is the technical definition but
it's not enough
just that you want to achieve buddhahood
because other people need stuff
he says we kind of got to add something
more what's he going to add
ichopa
you must
come to the realization
that there is no choice but for you to
become a buddha yourself
okay so you can say the definition of
bodhichitta
is the desire to reach buddhahood
so that you can help others but he says
somebody should have added something
here in there that said
you ain't got no choice
and you have to do it okay
you have to do it okay i i have to do it
he he objects who
pabonka is objecting to my trail
my trash said
i want to become a buddha
to help everybody
and and
kabunku's like is that the best you can
do
you know
and it's like well what else you want
he says i don't have any choice
i i gotta do it it's not like i wanna do
it
he says i have jack to your ah mata
i'm mata
i object to i wish
it's i ain't got no choice
okay i gotta do it okay
[Music]
don't say it's the wish for
enlightenment
it's the compulsion
you i have to do it i don't have a
choice i have to do it okay he wants it
stronger
my top comment means i ain't got no
choice i have to do it my top comment
is a idiom in tibetan that means uh
i ain't got no other choice i gotta do
it okay
he said now if you if if you
when you say a mata
the wish to achieve
if you mean i have no choice i'm with
you
but if you didn't think i have no choice
i know your definition's a little wimpy
okay i ain't got no choice i gotta do it
okay
now what's a person look like
when they're saying my top got me
i ain't got no choice well tim
i got no choice i gotta do
did they do that in chinese i don't know
in american english like
do you have to do it i got no choice
i got to do it you know okay so when you
see this
mudra i've gotten
[Music]
okay
it's like i got no choice
right when you see that picture don't
forget what it means
ain't got no choice
it doesn't mean i can't pay you back
today standing
[Music]
and then he says uh
uh
needless to say you it is not the wish
to achieve buddhahood just for yourself
okay just to do something for yourself
that's not the point
now jumping ninja hawks um because of
three of the steps you went through
already which was
champa my tree right
i want everyone else to be happy
ningxia i don't want anyone else to have
problems and clock them
i'll take i'll take the heat i'll get it
done and i don't care if nobody helps me
i don't even care if
everyone fights me i'll still do it okay
and that takes some spiritual maturity
when you try to help people and they
actually
hurt you back uh it takes some maturity
to say
okay i know you're
hate me
i'm still gonna pay your bills for next
month
you know like it takes some kind of
maturity to
to say you know
i know you're unhappy and i don't care
i'm still gonna make you happy okay all
right
all right ninja without any kind of what
do you call it
uh resentment
people hurt you back you help help help
help help people hurt your back you say
oh that's cool you know we do that to
our mom right
they help help help out and then we
criticize them they're like yeah okay
here i made your lunch also
you know
that's how she responds to criticism
okay
so
having bodhichitta with the right flavor
requires those previous steps
of
champa ninja and fluxon
i want you to have all good things
i don't want you to have any problems um
i'm on it i'll take care of it you don't
actually have to worry about anything
i'm taking care of it okay
those are required to have a properly
a body cheddar with the right taste
you gotta have those three thoughts
before i i want you to have everything
you want
i i don't want you to meet up with any
problems
and i'm on it
then you can have the proper body to
is produced by those three okay cool
and the way he says it here uh
let me see
[Music]
i want to show you another picture you
ready tim
it took me a while you know i looked up
on my uh photo
stock photo app
handcuffed people i got a lot of photos
that wouldn't be appropriate to show
i thought
my wife was next to us
but uh
the point of this picture
is uh
you don't have a choice by that point
in your mental state
even if you didn't want to help people
you couldn't help yourself you are
handcuffed
by your own love
you are handcuffed by you even if
you couldn't get out of this commitment
even if you wanted to okay you are
locked up locked in
you are locked in you don't have a
choice because you did the three steps
before
wanting people to have what they want
wanting to take away their pain taking
personal responsibility then when you
get to bodhichitta you're locked in
and
listen vision
mix of helpless
and vision you have this vision for what
you want
and you
you're out of control in a good way
you're out of control you couldn't back
out even if you
thought to
you couldn't get out of it okay your
your
previous
bodhichitta stamp study
is forcing you to keep going and you
don't have a choice anymore you're out
of control
in control finally in control by being
out of control
okay
[Music]
hey yeah we had it earlier i'll give a
hundred dollars
there's a long time ago
i'm not sure
yeah 100 bucks god he's the big bucks
man be careful people usually get
pregnant right after that
uh
and yeah
never mind
hey um yeah it means i i you know
yeah 100 bucks but you got to collect it
now new system
and then our gum
top
etude you know i understand
that it would be very noble
uh to work for all living beings i
understand it would be very noble
to want to take away all their pain
and i understand it would be very noble
to
to take responsibility
myself i understand it would be very
noble but is it even possible
is that kind of commitment even possible
[Music]
then he says something cool he says
can you achieve it
you can
and it's time honey
it's time
you know you think you're gonna get a
better time later you're an idiot
you know the time is
now
can i achieve that yes and you gotta do
it today
because who knows what's gonna be
tomorrow
who knows you're going to be alive who
knows what realm you you're going to be
one of those waggers
you know
you could be a dog tomorrow
and so pobonca's answer is very
beautiful
the guy says well i i don't know if i
can do that he says well god damn you
it's the last day this is the day you
gotta do it
there's not gonna be a better time
you know you're a human
you're still alive you're still
breathing you know you
don't ask me if you can do it you gotta
start not you gotta do it now you know
who knows where you're gonna be in 24
hours
you know that guy could push the nucleus
i mean we're very close you know rob
could be on a vacation tomorrow
and we don't know so he's just
yeah you can do it and you gotta do it
now okay okay never thought you can't do
that anyway talk about me there's no
better time
you have never
had a better chance than you have now
there's no better time to decide to do
this okay
because
you have the right mix
of body and mind long term jupiter 100
yeah 100 bucks
for mr stanley okay
yeah now he goes there he goes there
what's he saying
you got the
you got the body you got the prana you
got the chi you got the channels you got
the body you got the mind connected to
the body with the channels
you got it now
you're on the edge of becoming a buddha
you have a body with the prana and the
nadis and the chakras god
you're halfway there
just do your stupid yoga every morning
you know
it's gonna push you over the top
you a body
that was built for enlightenment
you have a body
that was pre-designed
to turn into an enlightened being's body
if you have those nadis
if you have that prana if you have those
chakras you were built for enlightenment
from the factory
okay
your your body was built jeong mai
you you were built with this channels
central channel you you were built to
become a buddha
so
do it
you don't know you can have dogs bodies
ain't got such good primer okay
they wag okay but that's about it
you got the perfect configuration
chronically
to do tantra
you can do yoga you can do temper you're
built for
enlightenment come on
you got everything you need okay
let's do it
it's a beautiful how he leaps to uh
the chakras and enchant it's so cool
he's like god you were built to become a
buddha what's wrong with you
you think you're gonna
get out of this bmw and get into a
toyota
taumah
okay you think you're gonna
do it later
you're in a bna you're getting done
i have a friend who has a bmw and a
tesla
depends on which
city is there at the time
i'm just kidding don't take it
personally
anybody who's doing good practice
will be successful they can't help it
it's not their fault
okay
probably their teacher
chinese
so listen
as far as body as far as your body
you're already half enlightened come on
take advantage of the ch of the chakras
you have
and the problem you have and
chinese sangi as far as the dharma you
got
sange dumbo
you got buddhist dharma you got as far
as teachings
you got
lord buddha's teachings are you crazy
you're gonna wait for something else
okay
and they
take the temperature
and
not only do you have buddhist teaching
but among the buddhist teaching you got
texan
take
bachembo mahayana
god
you're not stuck in the ability i'm a
school of vanilla
these are two masters
they're translating the classics for
those two you're not stuck you're in my
other you got mine
first of all
you're not those people with no
teachings
second of all you got
lord buddha's teachings
third of all you got mahayana hundred
dollars cutting what's he gonna say next
and among them mahayana you got
damn
100 bucks you gotta collect it new
system
okay that's exactly where he goes yeah
uh
how does he describe the word
tantrayana or diamond way
he says
say chiclat sangya
[Music]
ring
you have a system
which in a single lifetime can get you
there
so he doesn't say
montreal or tantriana he says the one
life system
you're sitting here
in a group of people
who at a place that was dedicated and
built
for the practice of the one life system
you had done
you know god you can't do it here
you
know don't say oh i wish them that i
could become a bit of good shut up
you know they built this place for
for vajrayogini practice this place was
built for budget meaning practice you
know and a lot of people
worked for many many years to get this
place ready for you i was with david
stump
a week ago
he brought a south african student
where's those south african states talk
a little funny but they're all right
and uh
yeah
and
khan you know you got a place that was
built for that don't tell me you can't
do it well
where are you going to go you know
you're going to go to cincinnati or
i don't know
i mean there's nothing there
you're here you know come on
you know don't tell me you're gonna do
it sometime somewhere
you can't do it here and then
you know there's actually no better
place in the universe to do it in here
okay seriously
so it was built for that this place was
selected for that the actual place was
selected for that
so
come on
you gotta do it okay
all right let's go through some pictures
slow
mr team
the first one is daniel with his hat
what does that women mean
yeah yeah i'm ready to do the work okay
i'm ready to work for others i'm up for
it okay
which
of the seven steps might this refer to
the last
three
well
mainly champa ninja and haksam
okay i think he did mention the fourth
one
no those three
those are the actual wanting to work and
then the foundation i wanted to work was
yeah equanimity know that your mom
think about the kindness i want to
repeat now okay okay
okay good
uh
now
what's the next picture represent
whose definition
my trans definition
of of of
bodhichitta right which is also called
for
chit
[Music]
then what's this next slide uh there was
one before that i mean uh
yeah that's my trans definition you
should learn the sanskrit
you should learn it it's not so hard
it'll put a good scene in your mind for
enlightenment
okay
so
just learn it's fun learn it
i used to keep a little notebook in my
shirt pocket
when i was first studying and i would
pull it out and
read it while i was walking places i i
would just open it up
and read it
i was learning sitar at the same time
and then i would go home and read this
on the way and one day i left this my
guru's
[Music]
music studio and i walked halfway home
studying these definitions
and i realized i forgot my shoes
and this is in the himalayas so
it's kind of a big deal and i ran back
to the sitar studios oh my god i forgot
my shoes he said now you're a real sit
down
now your your mind is elsewhere
instead of your feet okay
uh next picture
yeah thank you i ain't got any choice i
gotta do it i'm sorry
okay it's not enough to say
i want enlightenment for all living
beings my trail was
wrong
or incomplete okay i don't got a choice
i gotta do this thing
i'm compelled to do this thing
i can't get out of it okay
all right next one
it got worse okay
i'm chained by my commitment okay like i
gotta do this thing i i don't have a
choice
all right next picture
what is that we didn't do this picture
100 bucks
i know it's piano
come on you guys can do it
yeah yeah
you got the channel
venice has got the channel and you got
canna canal
okay don't forget you got alex you gotta
collect okay
yeah
she's probably
she's probably gonna run out of money
today so get to her early
thank you
yeah
who's spanish
all of us
yeah we have the channel we have the
channels right okay we got the necessary
canals okay
now if you can explain this last one i
might let you go to breakfast early
yeah
you can't go to breakfast early we're
gonna keep going no
yeah
diamond way okay
as far as
capacity
you were built to get enlightened
they put the chakras in you
they put the channels in you they put
the prana in you
you personally your personal body
was built for enlightenment from the
factory
seriously
okay
and as far as the dharma you are
sitting in the epicenter of tantric
practice on this planet
okay not bad
good
some questions
what are you waiting for what are you
waiting for
all right we have a little bit of time
and i i i'm a firm believer that you
shouldn't waste
but we have five minutes extra
so i'm gonna dip into the next class
slightly okay
here we go
tim's like ah i'm thinking
oh in fact i didn't send it to you yet
probably have some kind of connection
there
i'll just read it to you okay don't
worry about it
we'll look at the photos tomorrow okay
[Music]
say
remy
is a famous movement in tibet uh
in tibetan buddhism called rime re means
[Music]
non-aligned school
so there came to be a school called the
non-aligned school they weren't
connected to the galoopas and the
ningmas or the kagyus or the
they sakias they were they called
themselves the non-aligned school and of
course that became a
school
and people said i'm a real man you know
and you're like okay okay it's all right
so
uh
sorry
but here it means uh
it doesn't matter uh what school of
tibet you are in
or what school of ancient india you're
in
uh we are all uh fortunate that we all
have this teaching
uh that you can get you in line okay
jetson
uh but
so in general
it's true that uh
re-me without regard to what school
you're practicing
they can all bring you enlightenment in
one lifetime if the tantric teachings
in all schools can bring you
enlightenment in one lifetime
now whenever some
tibetan says we're all the same
he'll tell you immediately afterwards
why
we're special
okay and it's true okay so anyway look
you can get enlightenment one lifetime
in all the various traditions of tibet
if you practice the secret teachings
but
you know here in the tomkapa system
in 12 years
you can reach your goal in 12 years okay
it's possible
to reach your goal in 12 years and
that's a very famous number
you know you can reach uh in light and
that comes from the tantras that comes
from ancient india okay you
oh sorry you can't reach your goal in 12
years you know in sangha or new new it's
possible and delay young
you could also speed things up
from the 12 years okay
and
here's oh you don't have the picture
okay
low soon
three years okay it there is a system
inside of some purpose system where you
could achieve tantric enlightenment
within three years okay
so he said look
you have a body that was built for
enlightenment you are sitting in a place
that was built for that practice
and
you have a teaching that
any teaching from tibet you could
achieve in one lifetime
but you in particular if you followed
some compass
teachings you could achieve it in 12
years so even three years
san gabriel nursing deny cancer notices
and it's happened a lot of times before
okay
and
you can just
read these religious histories
biographies of these people and you can
see what happened to them
so there are these accounts you can read
them king of the dharma
you can get it online by email
easy
okay i i like it i have it on my
computer i look at it every once in a
while
okay so you have this
credible believable
uh
histories of people that you can read
and study and and the king of the dharma
book is a good example if you study that
book carefully
you can understand why he achieved
enlightenment in one lifetime okay
okay and uh
you'd be crazy not to read that book
from time to time
because uh
it's all there okay that's what he's
saying go list go read these books go
read these histories you can see what
happened to people
so don't believe me
all right gaywadi
me
welcome
and
we'll see you
tomorrow
and